I'm here today to talk to you about a very powerful little word,
انا هنا اليوم لأحدثكم عن كلمة صغيرة وقوية جدا
one that people will do almost anything
كلمة، يقوم الناس بفعل أي شيء تقريبا
to avoid becoming.
كي لا يصبحوها
Billion-dollar industries thrive
تزدهر صناعات بمليارت الدولارات
because of the fear of it,
بسبب الخوف منها
and those of us who undeniably are it
وأولئك الذين هم تلك الكلمة بلا شك
are left to navigate a relentless storm
يتركون للإبحار خلال عاصفة شديدة
surrounding it.
تحيط بهم
I'm not sure if any of you have noticed,
لست متأكدة فيما لو كان أحدكم قد لاحظ
but I'm fat.
لكن أنا سمينة
Not the lowercase, muttered-behind-my-back kind,
ليس ذلك النوع المخفي كالتمتمة من وراء ظهري
or the seemingly harmless chubby or cuddly.
أو الكلمات التي تبدو غير مؤذية؛ ممتلئة أومحبوبة
I'm not even the more sophisticated voluptuous or curvaceous kind.
لست حتى ذلك النوع الأكثر تنمقا مثيرة للشهوة أو ذات انحناءات
Let's not sugarcoat it.
دعونا لا نزينها.
I am the capital F-A-T kind of fat.
أنا سمينة بكل ما تحمله الكلمة من معنى
I am the elephant in the room.
أنا الفيل في الغرفة.
When I walked out on stage,
عندما ظهرت على المسرح
some of you may have been thinking,
قد يكون بعضكم فكر في نفسه
"Aww, this is going to be hilarious,
سيكون هذا مثيرا للضحك
because everybody knows that fat people are funny."
فالجميع يعلم أن السمينين يجيدون الإضحاك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or you may have been thinking, "Where does she get her confidence from?"
وقد تكونوا قد فكرتم " من أين لها بهذه الثقة ؟"
Because a confident fat woman is almost unthinkable.
لأن وجود إمراة سمينة واثقة من نفسها أمر من غير الممكن خطوره على الفكر
The fashion-conscious members of the audience
الأعضاء المهتمين بالأزياء والأناقة ضمن الحضور
may have been thinking how fabulous I look
من الممكن أن يكونوا حدثوا أنفسهم عن مدى روعة إطلالتي
in this Beth Ditto dress --
بهذا الفستان من تصميم بيث ديتو
(Cheers)
(تصفيق)
thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم
Whereas some of you might have thought,
بينما قد يكون البعض الآخر فكر
"Hmm, black would have been so much more slimming."
"ممم كان اللون الأسود سيجعلها تبدو أكثر نحافة"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You may have wondered, consciously or not,
قد تكونوا قد تساءلتم بوعي أو بغير وعي
if I have diabetes, or a partner,
فيما لو كنت أعاني من مرض السكر أو إن كان لدي شريك
or if I eat carbs after 7pm.
أو إذا كنت أتناول الكربوهيدرات بعد السابعة .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You may have worried that you ate carbs after 7pm last night,
قد تكونوا قلقين بشان تناولكم كربوهيدرات بعد السابعة الليلة الماضية،
and that you really should renew your gym membership.
وبأن عليكم تجديد عضويتكم بالنادي الرياضي
These judgments are insidious.
هذه أحكام لئيمة
They can be directed at individuals and groups,
قد يتم إطلاقها على الأفراد والجماعات
and they can also be directed at ourselves.
ويمكن أيضا أن نطلقها على أنفسنا
And this way of thinking is known as fatphobia.
وهذا النوع من التفكير هو ما يسمى رهاب السمنة.
Like any form of systematic oppression,
وكغيره من أنواع الاضطهاد الممنهج
fatphobia is deeply rooted in complex structures
فإن رهاب السمنة يتجذر في أعماق الأنظمة المعقدة
like capitalism, patriarchy and racism,
مثل الرأسمالية والبطريركة والتمييز العنصري،
and that can make it really difficult to see,
وهذا ما يجعل رؤيتها صعبة جدا
let alone challenge.
وذلك غير التحديات
We live in a culture
نحن نعيش في ثقافة
where being fat is seen as being a bad person --
يرى فيها الشخص السمين على إنه شخص سيء
lazy, greedy, unhealthy, irresponsible
كسول، طماع، غير صحي، غير مسؤول
and morally suspect.
ومتهم أخلاقيا.
And we tend to see thinness
ونميل لرؤية النحافة
as being universally good --
على أنها جيدة عالمياً
responsible, successful,
فنحن مسؤولين، وناجحين
and in control of our appetites, bodies and lives.
ومسيطرين على شهيتنا وأجسمانا وحياتنا
We see these ideas again and again
ونرى هذه الأفكار مرارا وتكرارا
in the media, in public health policy,
في الإعلام وفي سياسة الصحة الشعبية
doctors' offices,
مكاتب الأطباء
in everyday conversations
وفي محادثاتنا اليومية
and in our own attitudes.
وفي مواقفنا الشخصية
We may even blame fat people themselves
حتى أننا قد نلقي باللوم على الأشخاص البدينين أنفسهم
for the discrimination they face
على التمييز الذي يتعرضون إليه
because, after all, if we don't like it, we should just lose weight.
لأنه في النهاية اذا لم يعجبنا الوضع فكل ما علينا فعله هو خسارة الوزن.
Easy.
بسهولة
This antifat bias has become so integral, so ingrained
هذا الميل نحو اللا سمنة قد أصبح متكاملا جدا ومتأصل جدا
to how we value ourselves and each other
في كيفية تقيمنا لأنفسنا ولبعضنا
that we rarely question why we have such contempt for people of size
حيث أننا نادرا ما نسال أنفسنا عن سبب احنقارنا للأشخاص ذو الأحجام الكبيرة
and where that disdain comes from.
وعن مصدر هذا الإزدراء.
But we must question it,
ولكن يجب علينا التساؤل عن ذلك
because the enormous value we place on how we look
لأن القيمة الهائلة التي نعطيها لأشكالنا
affects every one of us.
تؤثر في كل واحد منا
And do we really want to live in a society
وهل نرغب فعليا بالعيش في مجتمع
where people are denied their basic humanity
يسلب فيه الناس إنسانيتهم الأساسية
if they don't subscribe to some arbitrary form of acceptable?
إذا لم يشتركوا في تشكيلة اعتباطية لما هو مقبول؟
So when I was six years old,
عندما كنت في السادسة من عمري
my sister used to teach ballet to a bunch of little girls in our garage.
كانت أختي تدرب الباليه لبضعة فتيات صغيرات في كراج منزلنا
I was about a foot taller and a foot wider than most of the group.
كنت أطول بقدم وأعرض بقدم من معظم الفتيات في المجموعة
When it came to doing our first performance,
عندما حان موعد تقديم عرضنا الأول
I was so excited about wearing a pretty pink tutu.
كنت متحمسة بشدة لارتداء التنورة القصيرة الزهرية الجميلة
I was going to sparkle.
كنت سألمع
As the other girls slipped easily into their Lycra and tulle creations,
وبينما ارتدت الفتيات الأُخريات التصاميم المصنوعة من الليكرا والتول بسهولة
not one of the tutus was big enough to fit me.
لم تكن أي من التنانير بمقاسي.
I was determined not to be excluded from the performance,
كنت عازمة على عدم التعرض للاستثناء من العرض
so I turned to my mother
فلجأت إلى أمي
and loud enough for everyone to hear
وبصوت عال يسمعه الجميع
said, "Mom, I don't need a tutu.
قلت لها " أمي لا أحتاج إلى توتو ( مقاس 2)
I need a fourfour."
أحتاج الى فورفور (اربعةاربعة )--اي مقاس
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Thanks, Mom.
شكرا أمي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And although I didn't recognize it at the time,
ورغم عدم ملاحظتي لذلك آنذاك
claiming space for myself in that glorious fourfour
إلا أن مطالبتي بمكان لي في تلك التنورة الفورفور المتألقة
was the first step towards becoming a radical fat activist.
كانت الخطوة الأولى نحو تحولي إلى ناشطة سمنة ثائرة
Now, I'm not saying that this whole body-love thing
الآن أنا لا أُخبركم بأن موضوع حب أجسادكم هذا
has been an easy skip along a glittering path of self-acceptance
كان قفزة سهلة خلال طريق تقبل الذات المتلألئ
since that day in class.
بدأتها منذ ذلك اليوم في الحصة .
Far from it.
بزمن بعيد عنها
I soon learned that living outside what the mainstream considers normal
سرعان ما تعلمت أن العيش بمنىء عن ما يعتبره الغالبية طبيعيا
can be a frustrating and isolating place.
يمكن أن يكون مكانا محبطا ومنعزلا.
I've spent the last 20 years unpacking and deprogramming these messages,
لقد أمضيت عشرين سنة في تفريغ تلك الرسائل والتخلص من برمجتها في العقول
and it's been quite the roller coaster.
وقد كان الأمر بمثابة ركوب أفعوانية
I've been openly laughed at, abused from passing cars
لقد تعرضت للسخرية والإساءة من السيارات المارة
and been told that I'm delusional.
قيل لي إني واهمة.
I also receive smiles from strangers
لكني أيضا تلقيت ابتسامات من غرباء
who recognize what it takes to walk down the street
عرفوا معنى كونك تسير في الشارع
with a spring in your step and your head held high.
بخطوة ثابتة ورأس مرفوع
(Cheer)
(تحية)
Thanks.
شكرا
And through it all, that fierce little six-year-old has stayed with me,
وعلى طول الطريق، بقيت فتاة الستة أعوام القوية تلك معي
and she has helped me stand before you today
وساعدتي في الوقوف أمامكم اليوم
as an unapologetic fat person,
كشخص سمين لا يعتذر عن سمنته
a person that simply refuses to subscribe
شخص ببساطة يرفض الإشتراك
to the dominant narrative
بالأحاديث السائدة
about how I should move through the world in this body of mine.
حول الكيفية التي يجب علي التحرك فيها بهذا العالم بجسم كهذا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And I'm not alone.
وأنا لست وحيدة في ذلك
I am part of an international community of people
فأنا جزء من مجتمع عالمي من الأشخاص
who choose to, rather than passively accepting
الذين اختاروا اختيارا ؛ ليس مجرد قبولا سلبيا
that our bodies are and probably always will be big,
بأن أجسادنا كبيرة وستبقى كذلك دائما على الأرجح
we actively choose to flourish in these bodies as they are today.
قررنا بإيجابية أن نزدهر بهذه الأجساد كما هي اليوم
People who honor our strength and work with, not against,
وأناس يقدرون قوتنا ويعملون ، مع لا ضد،
our perceived limitations,
قدراتنا المرجوة
people who value health
الناس الذين يقدرون الصحة
as something much more holistic
بمنظور أشمل
than a number on an outdated BMI chart.
من كونها أرقاما إحصائية قديمة
Instead, we value mental health, self-worth and how we feel in our bodies
بدلا من ذلك نقوم بتقدير الصحة العقلية والقيمة الذاتية وكيف نشعر بأجسامنا
as vital aspects to our overall well-being.
كمحاور أساسية للحياة الصحية
People who refuse to believe that living in these fat bodies
الناس الذين يرفضون فكرة كون عيشنا بهذه الأجساد الممتلئة
is a barrier to anything, really.
تشكل حاجزا أمام قدرتنا على فعل أي شيء، حقاً
There are doctors, academics and bloggers
هنالك أطباء وأكاديميين ومدونين،
who have written countless volumes
قاموا بكتابة عدد لا يحصى من المقالات
on the many facets of this complex subject.
حول الكثير من وجوه هذا الموضوع الشائك
There are fatshionistas who reclaim their bodies and their beauty
هنالك ( متبعات موضة) يحسننون مظهر أجسادهم وجمالهم
by wearing fatkinis and crop tops,
من خلال ارتداء ملابس المخصصة للسمان والقمصان التي تغطي الخصر
exposing the flesh that we're all taught to hide.
مظهرين اللحم الذي تعلمنا كلنا إخفاءه
There are fat athletes
هناك رياضيين سمان
who run marathons, teach yoga or do kickboxing,
يركضون الماراثون أو يعلمون اليوغا أو يمارسون الملاكمة الحرة
all done with a middle finger firmly held up to the status quo.
يفعلون كل هذا رافعين إصبعهم الوسطى بقوة في وجه الوضع الراهن
And these people have taught me that radical body politics
وقد علمني هؤلاء إن السياسات المتأصلة فيما يتعلق بالأجساد
is the antidote to our body-shaming culture.
هي الترياق لثقافة التعييب بالأجساد.
But to be clear, I'm not saying that people shouldn't change their bodies
لكن للتوضيح، لا أقول إنه لا يجب على الناس تغيير أجسادهم
if that's what they want to do.
إذا كان هذا هو ما يرغبون بفعله
Reclaiming yourself can be one of the most gorgeous acts of self-love
تحسين نفسك هو واحد من أروع مظاهر حب الذات
and can look like a million different things,
وهنالك ملايين من الأشياء التي تندرج تحت ذلك
from hairstyles to tattoos to body contouring
من قصات الشعر الى الوشم الى نحت الجسم
to hormones to surgery and yes, even weight loss.
الى الهرمونات الى العمليات ونعم، حتى خسارة الوزن
It's simple: it's your body,
الموضوع بسيط، إنه جسمك أنت
and you decide what's best to do with it.
وأنت هو من يقرر الأفضل بالنسبة له
My way of engaging in activism
طريقتي في العمل كناشطة
is by doing all the things that we fatties aren't supposed to do,
هي أن أقوم بفعل كل الأعمال التي يحظر علينا نحن السمان القيام بها
and there's a lot of them,
وهنالك الكثير منها،
inviting other people to join me and then making art about it.
أقوم بدعوة الآخرين للانضمام إلي وصنع من الأمر فناً
The common thread through most of this work
والخيط المشترك بين غالبية هذه الأنشطة
has been reclaiming spaces that are often prohibitive to bigger bodies,
هو المطالبة بأماكن غالبا ما تمنع عن السمان
from the catwalk to club shows,
ابتداءا من عروض الأزياء حتى عروض النوادي
from public swimming pools to prominent dance stages.
من المسابح العامة حتى منصات الرقص الشهيرة
And reclaiming spaces en masse is not only a powerful artistic statement
وعملية المطالبة بالأماكن إجمالا ليست تصريحا فنيا فحسب
but a radical community-building approach.
وإنما توجها ثوريا لبناء المجتمع
This was so true of "AQUAPORKO!" --
كان الفريق "الأكوابوركو" تصديقا لذلك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
the fat fem synchronized swim team
فريق من السباحات السمان
I started with a group of friends in Sydney.
بدأت بمجموعة من الأصدقاء في سيدني
The impact of seeing a bunch of defiant fat women
كان أثر رؤية مجموعة من النساء السمان
in flowery swimming caps and bathers
في أغطية رأس وملابس سباحة موردة
throwing their legs in the air without a care
رافعات أقدامهم بالهواء بلا اكتراث
should not be underestimated.
أثرا لا يمكن الاستهانة به
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Throughout my career, I have learned that fat bodies are inherently political,
خلال مسيرتي المهنية ، تعلمت أن الأجساد السمينة سياسية بالفطرة
and unapologetic fat bodies
والأجساد السمينة غير الآسفة
can blow people's minds.
لديها القدرة على إثارة دهشة الناس
When director Kate Champion,
عندما طلبت المخرجة كايت تشامبيون
of acclaimed dance theater company Force Majeure,
مخرجة الرقصة المسرحية كومباني دانس ميجور
asked me to be the artistic associate
أن أكون المشاركة الفنية
on a work featuring all fat dancers,
في عمل يضم جميع الراقصات السمان
I literally jumped at the opportunity.
قفزت على هذه الفرصة حرفيا
And I mean literally.
أعني حرفيا.
"Nothing to Lose" is a work made in collaboration with performers of size
(لا شيء لنخسره) هو عمل فني تم بالتعاون مع راقصات كبيرات الحجم
who drew from their lived experiences
استقين من تجاربهن الشخصية
to create a work as varied and authentic as we all are.
لصناعة عمل متنوع وأصيل مثلنا تماما
And it was as far from ballet as you could imagine.
وكان بعيدا كل البعد الذي يمكن تخيله عن الباليه.
The very idea of a fat dance work by such a prestigious company
كانت الفكرة المحضة وراء إنتاج عمل راقص لأشخاص سمان من قبل شركة مرموقة كهذه
was, to put it mildly, controversial,
كانت بتعبير بسيط ، مثيرة للجدل
because nothing like it had ever been done on mainstream dance stages before
إذ انه لم يسبق لأحد القيام بمثل هذا العمل على منصة رقص معروفة من قبل
anywhere in the world.
ولا في أي مكان في العالم
People were skeptical.
كان الناس متشككون
"What do you mean, 'fat dancers?'
"ما الذي تعنونه ب "راقصات سمينات"؟
Like, size 10, size 12 kind of fat?
تعنون بمقاس 10 او 12 هذا النوع من السمنة؟
Where did they do their dance training?
أين تلقوا تدريبهم على الرقص؟
Are they going to have the stamina for a full-length production?"
هل سيكون لديهم القدرة الجسدية على إتمام عرض طويل؟
But despite the skepticism,
ولكن رغم التشكيك،
"Nothing to Lose" became a sellout hit of Sydney Festival.
(لا شيء لنخسره) أصبحت الأكثر رواجا ومبيعا في مهرجان سيدني
We received rave reviews, toured,
تلقينا تقييمات مطرية ، تجولنا
won awards and were written about in over 27 languages.
حصدنا الجوائز وكتب عنا بأكثر من 27 لغة.
These incredible images of our cast were seen worldwide.
شوهدت هذه الصور الرائعة لفريقنا في مختلف أنحاء العالم.
I've lost count of how many times people of all sizes
لم تعد لدي المقدرة على عدد المرات التي أخبرني بها
have told me that the show has changed their lives,
أناس من جميع الأحجام عن مدى تغيير هذا العرض لحياتهم
how it helped them shift their relationship
كيف ساعدهم بتغيير علاقتهم
to their own and other people's bodies,
بأجسادهم وأجساد غيرهم.
and how it made them confront their own bias.
وكيف مكنهم من مواجهة تحيزهم الشخصي
But of course, work that pushes people's buttons
ولكن بالطبع فإن أي عمل يستثير مشاعر الناس
is not without its detractors.
لا يخلو من الذامين
I have been told that I'm glorifying obesity.
قيل لي أني أمجد السمنة المرضية
I have received violent death threats
وقد تلقيت تهديدات عنيفة بالقتل
and abuse for daring to make work that centers fat people's bodies and lives
وتمت مدايقتي لتجرؤي على القيام بعمل يجعل حياة وأجساد السمان محطاً للأنظار
and treats us as worthwhile human beings with valuable stories to tell.
ويعاملنا نحن السمان كبشر يملكون قصصا ثمينة لتروى
I've even been called
وتمت تسميتي
"the ISIS of the obesity epidemic" --
"داعشية وباء السمنة المرضية"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
a comment so absurd that it is funny.
تعليق سخيف لدرجة الإضحاك
But it also speaks to the panic,
إلا أنه يعبر أيضاً عن الهلع
the literal terror,
الإرهاب بمعناه الحرفي
that the fear of fat can evoke.
الذي يسببه الخوف من السمنة
It is this fear that's feeding the diet industry,
هذا هو الخوف الذي يمول صناع أغذية الحمية
which is keeping so many of us from making peace with our own bodies,
ويمنعنا من التصالح مع أجسادنا
for waiting to be the after-photo
الذي يجعلنا ننتظر تحولنا إلى الصورة بعد التحول
before we truly start to live our lives.
قبل أن نبدأ فعلياً بعيش حياتنا
Because the real elephant in the room here is fatphobia.
لأن الفيل الحقيقي في الغرفة اليوم هو رهاب السمنة
Fat activism refuses to indulge this fear.
ناشطي موضوع السمنة يرفضون تعزيز ذلك الخوف
By advocating for self-determination and respect for all of us,
عن طريق مناصرة حرية تقرير المصير والمطالبة بالاحترام لنا كلنا
we can shift society's reluctance to embrace diversity
نستطيع تغيير مقاومة الناس للتنوع والاختلاف
and start to celebrate the myriad ways there are to have a body.
ونبدأ بالاحتفال بالأشكال التي لاحصر لها من الأجساد
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)